<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The necessity dignity and duty of Gospel ministers discoursed of before the University of Cambridge.</title>
            <author>Hodges, Thomas, d. 1688.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1685</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 54 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A44072</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2321</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R13341</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11833126</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11833126</idno>
            <idno type="VID">49739</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A44072)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 49739)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 497:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The necessity dignity and duty of Gospel ministers discoursed of before the University of Cambridge.</title>
                  <author>Hodges, Thomas, d. 1688.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>30 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for William Rogers ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1685.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Thomas Hodges.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Matthew V, 13 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Pastoral theology.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:49739:1"/>
            <head>Advertiſement of Books printed for <hi>W. Rogers.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>SErmons preached upon ſeveral Occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, by the Right Reverend Father in God <hi>John Wilkins,</hi> D. D. and late Lord Biſhop of <hi>Cheſter.</hi> Never before Publiſhed.</p>
            <p>A Perſwaſive to <hi>Frequent Communion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Diſcourſe againſt <hi>Tranſubſtantiation.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:49739:1"/>
            <p>THE NECESSITY Dignity and Duty OF <hi>Goſpel Miniſters.</hi> Diſcourſed of before the UNIVERSITY OF CAMBRIDGE.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>William Rogers,</hi> at the <hi>Sun,</hi> over againſt St. <hi>Dunſtan</hi>'s Church in <hi>Fleetſtreet.</hi> 1685.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:49739:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:49739:2"/>
            <head>To the Worſhipfull <hi>PAUL WENTWORTH,</hi> Eſq;</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Honoured Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THE many Charities and Benefacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Sir <hi>Peter Wentworth</hi> your Brother in his Life-time, and the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny conſiderable Legacies he left to Miniſters at his Death, and particularly that to my ſelf, all paid by you with ſuch ſpeed and inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity, together with your own love to Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, manifeſted by the Settlement you have made upon the School at <hi>Northampton,</hi> and by your Love and Reſpects to good Miniſters may be a ſufficient Apology for my prefixing your Name to this Paper, which contains the ſubſtance of a Sermon ſometime preached to the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity of <hi>Cambridge,</hi> concerning <hi>The Neceſſity, Dignity and Duty of Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel Miniſters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir, may you long live a Pattern of good Works, and a Patron of good Men; and when you die may you leave a Name behind
<pb facs="tcp:49739:3"/> you better than of Sons and Daughters. May your Name and Memory be like the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of good <hi>Joſiah, Eccleſ. 49.</hi> like the compoſition of the Perfume, made by the Art of the Apothecary, ſweet as Honey in the Mouth of all that ſpeak of you, and as Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick at a Banquet of Wine in the Ears of all that hear of you.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Which is the hearty deſire of Worthy SIR,</salute>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your very Humble Servant,</hi> Thomas Hodges.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 6. l. 33. dele <hi>thirdly.</hi> P. 8. l. 9. for <hi>ejecit</hi> reade <hi>evomit.</hi> P. 12. after <hi>Ezekiel's Temple</hi> add <hi>Chriſt was typified.</hi> L. 32. for <hi>ſincerity</hi> reade <hi>fire.</hi> P. 15. l. 7. for <hi>trn</hi> reade <hi>turn.</hi> L. 24. for <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> reade <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. P. 16. l. 29. for <hi>are</hi> reade <hi>or.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:49739:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>MATT. 5.13.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Ye are the ſalt of the Earth: but if the ſalt have loſt his ſavour, wherewith ſhall it be ſalted? it is henceforth good for nothing, but to be caſt out, and to be trodden under foot of men.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THE Text is a part of <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Sermon on the Mount (after he had ſpent a whole Night in Prayer) to his new elect A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles; a kind of Ordination-Sermon, or elſe a <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio ad Clerum.</hi> The 14, 15 and 16 verſes contain a peculiar admonition to his Apoſtles (as Interpreters generally conceive) both concerning their Doctrine, and their Life and Converſation; and this under three metaphors or ſimilitudes, of Salt, of a City ſet on an Hill, and of Light. They are Light, they muſt not be put under a Buſhel, or in a dark Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorn; they muſt ſhine, to whom? to all that are in the Houſe; yea they muſt be burning and ſhining Lights, like <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt,</hi> both by their preaching and living, that others hearing their good Doctrine, and ſeeing their good Works, may glorifie their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther which is in Heaven. Again, they are a City ſet on an Hill, very conſpicuous, <hi>in omnium oculis,</hi> the eyes of the World are upon them; any erroneous Doctrine taught by them, or any miſcarriage in pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice in them, cannot be hid, but will prove very no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:49739:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> and ſcandalous. Thirdly, they are Salt, and the Salt of the Earth; neceſſary, uſefull and benefici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al to the world as Salt is; but they muſt be ſavoury ſalt, not ſaltleſs ſalt; if ſo, firſt, they become alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether unprofitable and contemptible; ſecondly, they are good for nothing, muſt expect to loſe their places and ſtations in the Church, to be caſt out, and to be expoſed to ſcorn and contempt, to be made vile a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the people, to be trodden under foot of men. Some I know (as <hi>Grotius</hi> and Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi> expound) extend this Scripture ſo far as to reach all Chriſtians, becauſe the Beatitudes are of general concernment, and becauſe they think the twelve Apoſtles were not called and ordained till afterwards, namely, till Chapter the 10th, but to the laſt it is anſwered, that in the Writings of the Evangeliſts, there be certain anticipations, that is, ſome things are ſet down af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, which were done before, and ſome things are ſet down before which were done after; and ſo here the inſtruction of the Apoſtles for the office and work of the Miniſtry ſeems to be the main ſcope of this Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, and therefore they may be reaſonably thought to be called or ordained before; as for the election of the Apoſtles, it is ſet down indeed afterwards in the tenth Chapter, but 'tis by reaſon or upon occaſion of the Evangeliſts recording then their commiſſion to preach. As to the other objection it may be anſwered, that though he preached in the audience of the people, and that in this Sermon he did teach his Followers many things in general, yet our bleſſed Saviour here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in did chiefly intend to inſtruct his twelve Apoſtles, whom he had newly choſen to be teachers of others. Thirdly, Ye, that is ye my Apoſtles and Miniſters, ye are the ſalt of the earth, that is, of men that dwell on the earth, 'tis your part and duty to ſeaſon them
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:49739:4"/> with the ſound Doctrine ye have heard, and with a converſation becoming the Goſpel: that ſo they may be preſerv'd from corruption and putrefaction. Ye are ſalt, not properly but by reſemblance; yet not in regard of their Perſons, but of their Miniſtry; hereby by this they were to make the corrupt natures, hearts, communications and converſations of men to become ſavoury, to ſeaſon them for God. And the Apoſtles are called the ſalt of the earth, that is, not of <hi>Judaea</hi> onely, but of the whole World. So our Saviour enlarged their Commiſſion, <hi>Matt.</hi> 28.19. <hi>Go therefore and teach all nations;</hi> now our Saviour am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plifieth the former reaſon, whereby he moved his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles to fidelity and diligence in their Office and Miniſtry, by letting them know, that otherwiſe they would be but unſavoury ſalt, incurable or hardly cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, unprofitable and contemptible; good for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but to be caſt out, and to be trodden under foot. A proverbial ſpeech to ſhew a thing of no worth or value, but that is ſcorn'd and deſpiſed great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. I ſhall endeavour by God's aſſiſtence to ſhew</p>
            <p n="1">1. That Miniſters are the ſalt of the earth, and that 'tis their duty to be ſavoury ſalt. 2. 'Tis poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſome Miniſters may prove unſavoury ſalt. 3. By what means this ſalt becomes unſavoury. 4. That this unſavoury ſalt is hardly curable. 5. That in this condition 'tis uſeleſs and unprofitable. 6. That un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſavoury ſalt or bad Miniſters, unfaithfull in their Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, are liable to ejection and contempt, or to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived and ſcorned, and to be troden under foot of men.</p>
            <p n="1">1. They are ſo, ſee the Text, ſee alſo <hi>Mark</hi> 9.50. and <hi>Luk.</hi> 14.34. Salt makes that which is inſipid and unſavoury to reliſh, it gives it a good taſte; ſo the word of God which Miniſters preach doth ſeaſon them, and render them acceptable to God: he will
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:49739:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> not ſpew them out of his mouth that believe and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey their word. <hi>Sal terrae dicuntur</hi> (ſaith one) <hi>quia totus orbis doctrinâ Apoſtolorum condiendus.</hi> A little ſalt ſeaſons a great deal of Proviſion. So the Apoſtles (though a few in number) did ſeaſon many Nations, <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles, Greeks</hi> and <hi>Romans,</hi> and others; yea they prevailed by their preaching <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſum ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minum genus inſipidum, Deóque ingratum quinimo abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minabile, quippe quod ejecit ex ore ſuo, jam olim in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulſam agens vitam, &amp; ſapidum Deóque gratum ac ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundum reddere.</hi> So <hi>Ludovicus Brugenſis.</hi> 1. By the preaching of the Goſpel to the world and their recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of it, mens perſons were made gratefull and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable and well pleaſing to God, which elſe he would have loathed and abominated. Hereby, ſaith one, <hi>Cibus Diaboli fit cibus Dei.</hi> 2. Mens Services and Sacrifices which they performed, were ſeaſoned to acceptation, by means of the Covenant of grace, revealed in the Goſpel, that covenant of Salt: elſe God would not have had that reſpect to them he had, for the ſacrifices of the wicked are an abomination to the Lord, and the reaſon is, becauſe they want this ſalt: for the Law ſaith, <hi>Every ſacrifice muſt be ſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned or ſalted with ſalt, Levit.</hi> 2.12. 3. By the word of God mens actions are rendred more ſavoury to God and Man. <hi>Omnis vítoe pars</hi> (ſaith one) <hi>ſine ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bo, inſulſa &amp; inſipida; ſicut ergo oblatio quoevis ſale condienda, ita quoevis actio, verbo condienda.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Salt its heat and acrimony doth reſiſt putrefaction; and ſo the Apoſtles and Miniſters, by preaching the word, by being inſtant in ſeaſon and out of ſeaſon, by reproving, rebuking, exhorting, do withſtand the corruptions of men, their corrupt natures, corrupt principles, corrupt hearts, rotten communications, and corrupt and filthy converſations. The word of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:49739:5"/> God preached (principally the Goſpel) is a means to dry up, and ſtaunch our fountain of Bloud, and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Corruption, which elſe would ſtream from us continually. Yea the Word (eſpecially the Goſpel) is better than ſalt; for <hi>Sal ad diuturnitatem aliquam ſervat; miniſterii vero ſal, ad aeternitatem:</hi> Again, ſalt preſerves freſh meat, which is already free from corruption, for a time: but, <hi>Sal miniſterii, homines, jam antè naturâ ſuâ faetidos, &amp; Deo abominabiles, à foetore &amp; putredine eximit.</hi> Further 'tis to be noted, that though the word reſemble ſalt in the good qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities of ſalt, yet not in the bad. As for example. 1. Sow a Land with ſalt and it makes a fruitfull Land barren and unfruitfull, but let the Church (God's field) be ſowed with the word, and it becomes fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full; ſome part of it to bring forth thirty, ſome ſixty, ſome an hundred fold. 2. Salt muſt be uſed in mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and moderation: too much ſalt makes meat nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſavoury nor wholſome, but the Goſpel admits of no <hi>nimium:</hi> Preach the word ſaith the Apoſtle to <hi>Timothy,</hi> be inſtant in ſeaſon and out of ſeaſon; and divers of the Fathers of old, and ſo Biſhop <hi>Hooker</hi> and Mr. <hi>Calvin</hi> of late, preached every day. 3. Salt makes drink unſavoury, <hi>Sal potum inſuavem efficit:</hi> hence <hi>James</hi> 3.12. ſalt water is oppoſed to ſweet: not ſo the word; <hi>Thy word is ſweet unto my taſte,</hi> ſaith <hi>David, yea ſweeter than honey unto my lips.</hi> Miniſters by reaſon of the word they preach are the ſalt of the earth: <hi>Trahit ad perſonas, quod eſt Doctrinae,</hi> ſaith <hi>Calvin, non tam ad Perſonas, quàm ad munus,</hi> ſaith <hi>Gualter;</hi> to the Apoſtolical or Miniſterial Function, teaching us, that 'tis the part and duty of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the word, to ſeaſon the Hearts of the Faithfull. And this brings us to the Duty of Miniſters. Ye are the ſalt of the earth, ye ought to be the ſalt of the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:49739:6"/> earth. <hi>Eſtis,</hi> ſaith one, <hi>id eſt, eſſe debetis, ad hoc e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecti &amp; ordinatià me eſtis Apoſtoli, ut ſitis.</hi> Miniſters muſt be ſavoury ſalt, they muſt have ſalt in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and thus muſt ſeaſon others. Salt it ſelf is earth (ſaith <hi>Spanhem.</hi>) but 'tis earth burnt and purged from its dregs. <hi>Ipſe ſal terra eſt, ſed terra expurgata à foecibus.</hi> So the Apoſtles and Miniſters they are Earth but purified by the Spirit of God, which is as Fire: <hi>Ex ſe terra ſunt, ſed terra expurgata &amp; excocta ſacro igne &amp; Domini Spiritu.</hi> 1. There is requiſite for a Miniſter <hi>ſal gratiae;</hi> we come not into the world ſalted with this ſalt. Yea, <hi>Grande opus eſt inſaliri,</hi> ſaith the Father, <hi>qui ſale conditur, gratiâ plenus eſt; in communi proverbio ſalſus dicitur gratioſus, &amp; à con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trario, inſulſus qui non habet gratiam.</hi> He that hath Grace in his Heart can ſpeak experimentally; can ſay, <hi>That which I have heard and ſeen declare I unto you,</hi> as 'tis 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.3. and with <hi>David, This poor man cried, and the Lord heard him;</hi> and again, <hi>Come ye children hearken unto me, and I will teach you what he hath done for my ſoul.</hi> 2. There is requiſite for a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter <hi>ſal eruditionis;</hi> that he be ſeaſoned with good Learning; ſome meaſure of Natural parts, and ſome meaſure of acquired Learning is very requiſite for a Miniſter: ſome knowledge men ought to have in the Tongues, eſpecially the Original Tongues, wherein the Scriptures were written; elſe if they conſult In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreters onely, in ſome places (ſaith one) the half hath not been told them. The milk of the word is then moſt ſincere, when drawn immediately from thoſe full Breaſts, the Hebrew and Greek Texts; whereas it becomes more dilute (ſaith one) by being filed through a Tranſlation; wherein part of the Cream ſliding in the paſſage it loſes ſomewhat of its delicious and genuine reliſh. This water of life being
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:49739:6"/> carried from its fountain, by derivation into other Tongues ſometimes loſeth of its high guſt and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Spirit. And as the Tongues ſo are alſo the Arts, Logick, natural Philoſophy, Hiſtory, Chronology, Geography, Aſtronomy, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> uſefull for a Miniſter, as is excellently ſhewed in a Treatiſe to that purpoſe by Mr. <hi>Reyner</hi> of <hi>Lincoln.</hi> 3. There's requiſite for a Miniſter <hi>Sal Sapientiae,</hi> the Salt of Wiſdom. <hi>Sicut in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulſum à cibo transfertur ad hominem; ita fatuum ab homine transfertur ad cibum: ſic à Martiali, betae in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſipidae, vocantur fatuae,</hi> an unwiſe or fooliſh man is <hi>inſulſus</hi> or without Salt. <hi>Apoſtoli ſal terrae vocantur, quia homines &amp; ſuâ ſapientià docere debent, &amp; ſuis mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus aedificare,</hi> ſo <hi>Maldonat.</hi> Miniſters ſhould be wiſe to divide the word of God aright, to give every one their portion in due ſeaſon, as a Workman that needs not to be aſhamed. <hi>Aaron</hi>'s Bells (ſaith one) muſt be wiſely rung; ſometimes in one tune, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in another as occaſion ſerves. A Miniſter had need be wiſe to diſcern mens Tempers and Diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; to chuſe the fitteſt ſeaſons to deal with them, to treat of ſutable Subjects, for variety of occaſions and occurrences; to be able <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to ſpeak up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the wheels, that his words may be like Apples of Gold in Pictures of Silver, <hi>Prov.</hi> 25.11. A wiſe Man will not ſend a Fool upon his Errand, and ſurely then a moſt wiſe God would have his Ambaſſadours ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned with Salt, to be throughly furniſhed to every good word and work; and to be wiſe unto the Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, even both of themſelves and of them that hear them. And as Miniſters muſt have Salt in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, ſo they muſt ſeaſon others, and this may be done two ways, by their Doctrine and their Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, or by their Preaching and by their Practice. 1. They muſt be ſure to preach always ſound, ſavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:49739:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> wholſome Doctrine, they muſt always avoid all unſound, rotten or unſavoury Doctrine: eſpecially they muſt preach Chriſt, he that is the Center, yea in a ſenſe, the α and ω of the Scripture ſhould be all in all in our Sermons. We ſhould above all as deſire to know nothing but Chriſt and him crucified, ſo preach nothing in compariſon of Chriſt and him crucified. 'Tis thought by the Salt required with e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Sacrifice, both in the Tabernacle, in <hi>Solomon</hi>'s Temple, and in <hi>Ezekiel</hi>'s Temple; and in Chriſt and by him it is, that God hath entered into a Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Grace with Man, and this Covenant is an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting Covenant, and ſo may be called a Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Salt, with this Covenant let Miniſters endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, as to ſeaſon themſelves, ſo to ſeaſon their Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, and their Auditours. Again Miniſters muſt not dawb and flatter, preach pleaſing things, ſow Pillows under Peoples Elbows, or throw Sugar upon them, when Salt is neceſſary. Their Sermons muſt have acrimony in them; what though it makes Mens wounds ſmart? It will keep them from rank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling. 'Tis a ſign of a weak and giddy Conſtitution of Soul, to deſire to have our Soul-food powdered with Sugar, rather than with Salt. God, of old, under the Law, required Salt in every Sacrifice, but yet he forbad Honey to be uſed in Sacrifices; and 'tis thought the reaſon was, becauſe Honey doth ferment. This may teach us not to preach Doctrines that are likely to puff up our ſelves or others, but let our Sermons rather (when occaſion ſerves) rebuke Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners ſharply, and let our Sermons be ſalted with ſincerity. I find that the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> his Spirit was ſtirred in him at <hi>Athens, Acts</hi> 17. When he ſaw the City wholly given to Idolatry. Miniſters muſt be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voury Salt, they muſt ſeaſon others, by a good Life
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:49739:7"/> and Converſation; and this by their words and by their works. 1. Their Speech muſt be ſavoury, ſeaſon'd with Salt, ſuch as may miniſter Grace to their Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, and this too out of the Pulpit, <hi>viz.</hi> in their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe and Communication with Men. No filthy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication, or rotten or unſavoury words muſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed out of their Mouths, their Throats muſt not be like an open Sepulchre, ſending out Stench and Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption. Theſe Watchmen muſt eſpecially ſet a watch at the Door of their Lips, leſt they offend with their Tongue. The Prieſt's Lips ſhould preſerve knowledge, and there ſhould always ſtand ready at the Door of their Lips, ſome good or ſavoury Speech, either a word of Inſtruction, or of admonition, or of reprehenſion. To this purpoſe, he had need to pray, that God would touch his Tongue with a Coal from the Altar, and be with his Mouth (as ſometimes with <hi>Moſes</hi>) that he may open his Lips, and ſhew forth his praiſe. 2. Miniſters muſt ſeaſon others by their good works, by works of Piety, Charity, Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy; as they muſt be lively in their preaching, ſo their Lives muſt be a Sermon. They muſt walk exemplarily before their Family, and before their Flock; labour they muſt, that they may ſay with the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> to others, be ye Followers of us, as we alſo are of Chriſt. 2. As good Miniſters are like Salt in its primitive and pure Eſtate, ſo are bad Miniſters like Salt too, but 'tis in its unſavoury and degenerate Eſtate. Salt may loſe its ſavour, and ſo Miniſters if they be, if they prove, unfaithfull, they are but unſavoury ſalt. It was the Puniſhment of <hi>Lot</hi>'s Wife, for looking back to <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> that ſhe was turn'd into a Pillar of Salt, and 'tis the Caſe and Condition of Miniſters, who are called Angels in Scripture, if they leave their ſtation, if they Apoſtatize; to be like unſavoury Salt, to be caſt out,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:49739:8"/> and to be trodden under foot of men. Yet as we reade of fallen Angels, and of Stars falling from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, ſo there are Miniſters, Angels of the Churches, and that are ſometimes compar'd to Stars, and in this our Saviour's Sermon, call'd the Light of the World; ſome Miniſters there have been who have proved faln Angels, and falling Stars, who have neither the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rim</hi> nor <hi>Thummim,</hi> neither purity of Doctrine, nor inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity of Life, but become unſavoury ſalt, altogether uſeleſs and unprofitable. We reade in Scripture of wicked Prieſts, Sons of <hi>Belial,</hi> Prieſts who made the people abhor the Sacrifices of the Lord; we reade of a <hi>Judas</hi> a Devil amongſt the twelve Apoſtles of our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, of falſe Teachers, and falſe Apoſtles, and falſe Prophets. St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> in his time complained, <hi>Non in Sacerdotibus Religio devota, non in Miniſtris fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des integra, non in moribus Diſciplina:</hi> there was a great defection it ſeems as to their Religion, their Faith, their Works, their Manners; their ſilver was become droſs, and their wine mixt with water. The truth is, the true Prophets had no greater enemies than the falſe Prophets of old; <hi>Ahab</hi>'s Prophets oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>Micaiah; Hananiah, Jeremiah; Amaziah</hi> Prieſt of <hi>Bethel</hi> the Prophet <hi>Amos, Am.</hi> Chap. 7. the Scribes and Phariſees and Prieſts our Bleſſed Saviour; the falſe Apoſtles the Apoſtle <hi>Paul;</hi> the <hi>Arians</hi> the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox; and afterwards, none more cruel or greater Perſecutors under the Papacy than their Biſhops and Prieſts. <hi>Corruptio optimi eſt peſſima,</hi> Men of the beſt Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, if corrupted, prove the worſt. But this truth, that ſalt may prove unſavoury, that there may be clouds without water, and wandring and falling Stars, falſe Teachers and bad Miniſters, this hath more need of a lamentation that it is ſo, than of any proof or confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation that it may be ſo. But if it be ſo, why is it
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:49739:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> thus? How is the Gold and Silver become droſs? How comes this ſalt to be unſavoury? To this I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, That ſalt is ſometimes made of water taken out of the Sea, and if you put it into the Sea again it loſes its virtue. Miniſters are called and taken out of the World, that troubleſome Sea that always is caſting out mire and dirt; and if they trn thither again, if they deſire and affect to live in trouble, in Law-ſuits, Quarrels and Brangles with their Neighbours, this renders them and their Miniſtry uſeleſs and unprofi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table.</p>
            <p>Contentiouſneſs marrs a Miniſters good Savour. 2. Some Salt (or at leaſt the matter of which it is made) is taken out of the Earth; and if it be laid into the Earth again, if buried in the Earth again, I ſuppoſe it will ſoon loſe its ſavour: So Miniſters are in reſpect of their Calling, call'd out of the Earth, to a ſpiritual, high and heavenly Calling, but if they fall back again to the love of the preſent world, of earth and earthly things, a thouſand to one but they become unſavoury and unprofitable. Covetouſneſs marrs a Miniſter's ſavour. 'Tis farther obſervable that the corruption of ſalt is called an infatuation; <hi>Sal in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſipidus dicitur,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>infatuari,</hi> to be infatuated or grown fooliſh. So in the Text and in <hi>Luke</hi> 14.34. hence fooliſh men are called <hi>inſulſi, inſipidi,</hi> as ye would ſay, men without ſalt, unſeaſonable, unſavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry perſons. And if once Miniſters that ſhould be wiſe as the Angels of God, in ſome ſenſe, become <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi>'s fools, given up to any habituated courſe of ſin, eſpecially to uncleanneſs, to commit folly, to be as one of the fools, no marvel then if they ſoon loſe their ſavour, and are ſaid to be infatuated; even are like to the unſavoury ſalt in the Text, and being ſo, are incurable or hardly curable, for as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:49739:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>Bray a fool in a mortar, yet will not his folly depart from him:</hi> and ſo I come to the fourth particular. Bad Miniſters are hardly curable, <hi>Inemendabil<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s penè conditio mali miniſtri: ſalis ſapor, &amp; ſolis ſplendor, in ſeſe ita eſt, ut aliis communicetur, amiſſus non reparetur.</hi> The ſight of the eye, if once totally loſt, is irrecove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable without a miracle. If the Fountain be dried whence ſhall that be ſupplied? If the light that is in you be darkneſs how great is that darkneſs? If the heart once loſe its vital heat there is no remedy: and ſo here, <hi>Non eſt ſalis ſal,</hi> who ſhall teach the teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers? <hi>Non eſt Doctor Doctorum,</hi> ſaith one, <hi>&amp; quis cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diet ipſos cuſtodes?</hi> ſay we: which made the Father cry out, <hi>Quis unquam vidit prolapſum Clericum agentem Poenitentiam?</hi> And ſo I come to the fifth particular I propounded to you, namely, That unſavoury ſalt is uſeleſs and unprofitable, and ſo are bad Miniſters: if Money be broken the Goldſmiths can uſe it: cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted and putrified fleſh, although it is not man's meat, yet the Dogs will eat it: old threed-bare Cloaths and Rags, though they are not fit to be worn, yet they are good to make Paper, or they are good for the Dunghil, and to fat the Land, and to make that fruitfull. Wine that has loſt its flavour, and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Spirits, yet will make Vinegar. But bad Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters for the moſt part are good for nothing; like the Vine the Prophet <hi>Ezekiel</hi> ſpeaks of Chap. 15. If it bear not Grapes it is good for nothing but to be burnt, it is not like other Trees. Wicked Miniſters are bad Miniſters, are good for nothing. God will pluck out their right eyes, and dry up their right arms; that is, he will bereave them of their former abilities: ſee <hi>Zechariah</hi> 11.17. he will blaſt their parts, and ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them uſeleſs; yea God and Man join to puniſh wicked Miniſters: God caſts them off, and Man caſts
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:49739:9"/> them out: As wicked Miniſters are like ſalt in its corrupt eſtate, ſo is the portion of unſavoury ſalt their puniſhment; unſavoury ſalt is to be caſt out and trodden under foot; and ſo <hi>Inutilis miniſter loco mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vendus.</hi> No Loyterers muſt ſtay in God's Vineyard, there muſt be none but Labourers in his Harveſt, the Lord of the Vineyard and of the Harveſt will caſt out the unprofitable ſervant, ſuch muſt be caſt out of the Church, as we throw out unſavoury ſalt out of the Salt-cellar and out of the Salt-box. God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf the Lawgiver, of his Church and of the World hath laid this burthen on Miniſters, in the caſe of <hi>Eli</hi>'s Sons, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.30. Conform to this general rule King <hi>Solomon</hi> put out <hi>Abiathar</hi> from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing High-Prieſt, and put <hi>Zadok</hi> in his place: And the pious and learned <hi>Spanhemius</hi> in his Examination of <hi>Salmero</hi> his Gloſs upon this place ſaith plainly that evil Paſtours, Teachers and Biſhops, <hi>Non tantùm me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reri abjectionem &amp; contemptum, ſed reverâ abjiciendos eſſe, niſi emendari poſſunt &amp; corrigi.</hi> And we find in <hi>Cyprian</hi> the Depoſition of <hi>Baſilides,</hi> and the putting <hi>Sabinus</hi> in his place, <hi>Ep.</hi> 68. Yea the ſame <hi>Cyprian</hi> writes to <hi>Stephanus,</hi> that <hi>Martianus</hi> might be reſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned from hurting the Church; <hi>Et alius in locum ejus ſubſtituatur,</hi> and that another might be ſubſtituted in his place, <hi>Ep.</hi> 67. and indeed, why ſhould Wolves be ſuffered among <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s Flock, and in his Fold? So then caſt out bad Miniſters muſt be, and that with ſcorn and contempt, the Prophet <hi>Malachi</hi> threatens, <hi>Mal.</hi> 2.3. that wicked Prieſts ſhall be taken away as dung, or with it. They ſend out a ſtinking ſavour in the noſtrils of God and Man. And whenas good Miniſters are highly honoured by Men, by good Men, and ſometimes by wicked Men, (wicked <hi>Herod</hi> ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured <hi>John Baptiſt</hi>) wicked Miniſters ſhall be caſt
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:49739:10"/> out of the good opinions, and out of the affections of Men; and they may expect to be caſt out of their places and employments, and at laſt to be caſt out with the unprofitable Servant into outer darkneſs. Hear a memorable ſaying of Cardinal <hi>Cajetan,</hi> who commenting on this Text, when the <hi>French</hi> Army ſacked <hi>Rome,</hi> viz. <hi>May</hi> 6th 1527. writes thus, <hi>We the Prelats of</hi> Rome, <hi>do now find the truth of this by wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full experience, being become a ſcorn and prey, not to Infidels but Chriſtians, by the moſt righteous judgment of God, becauſe we, who by our places ſhould have been the ſalt of the earth had loſt our ſavour, and were good for little elſe but looking after the outward Rites and Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies of the Church.</hi> Hence is it, that together with us, this whole City comes to be trodden under foot, <hi>Evanuimus,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>ac ad nihilum utiles, niſi ad ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternas ceremonias, externáque bona,</hi> &amp;c. The truth is, as good Miniſters are a good, a ſweet ſavour unto God in them that periſh, and in them that are ſaved; ſo bad ones are unſavoury ſalt, and as vile as dung that ſends forth a moſt noiſome and ſtinking ſavour con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</note> 1. This may inform us of the great neceſſity and uſefulneſs of the Miniſtry and of its continuance, and conſequently the neceſſity and uſefulneſs of Univerſities, Colleges and Schools of Learning, the Nurſeries of Preachers, and of the Sons of the Prophets. They are the ſalt of the earth; as long as men are ſubject and liable to corruption in Doctrine or Manners, ſo long will Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel Preachers be neceſſary. Monopolies of ſalt are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurious to the weal of the Commonwealth, much more injurious are they, both to the Church and Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, who would wholly deprive us of the office of Miniſters and Preachers of the word.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:49739:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>2. Hence we may learn the reaſon why good Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters are ſo ſlighted in the world, they are ſalt, their Sermons are full of acrimony, they make mens wounds ſmart: thoſe words in the Text, ſaith <hi>Chem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitius,</hi> are brought as a reaſon of what went before, <hi>viz.</hi> why the world ſhould perſecute the Apoſtles, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they were the ſalt of the earth; their work was to reprove ſinners ſharply, and ſinners will uſually hate and perſecute him that reproveth in the Gate or in the Pulpit, thoſe that dawb with untempered mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, thoſe that ſew Pillows under ſinners Elbows, thoſe that preach <hi>Placentia,</hi> pleaſing things, thoſe that skin over wounds ſhall be accepted and well en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained, but ſinners love not thoſe that will apply corroſives, that will apply ſalt to ſearch their wounds and make them ſmart, though this method and means moſt tend to the making a perfect and thorough Cure.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Hence Miniſters may learn their duty, they are ſalt, and they muſt have the properties of ſalt in their preaching.</p>
            <p>Now 'tis obſerved that the properties of ſalt applied to raw fleſh or freſh wounds are principally three. Firſt, Salt will bite and fret, being of nature hot and dry. Secondly, it makes it ſavoury unto our taſte. Thirdly, it preſerveth meats from putrefaction, by drawing out of them ſuperfluous moiſtneſs. So Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters muſt apply the word of God to their Auditors, firſt, preaching the Law, thereby making them ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of their ſins, giving them no eaſe in them, but making them cry out as they, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.37. <hi>Men and brethren what ſhall we doe?</hi> ſecondly, Miniſters muſt preach the Goſpel to them, that men being ſenſible of their corruption, like rottenneſs in their Souls, may by the ſpirit of God be ſeaſoned with Grace, may be
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:49739:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> reconciled unto God, and made ſavoury in his No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrils. Thirdly, both Law and Goſpel muſt be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſed by Miniſters, that thereby ſin and corruption may be daily more and more mortified and conſumed in the hearts and lives of their hearers, even as ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous humours are dried up by ſalt. And Miniſters muſt endeavour to be ſeaſoned themſelves with the word that they may be the more able and fit to ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon others. Fourthly, Hence the people may learn to ſuffer the word of reproof; when we have a cut or wound in our fleſh we put ſalt upon it, to hinder it from rankling and corruption, and ſhall we not pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently and quietly ſuffer the word of reproof from our Teachers, though it make our Conſciences ſmart again, becauſe it tends to the health of our Souls? Fifthly, Hence we may learn all of us what we are by nature, we are like fleſh ſubject to corruption, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſavoury fleſh; yea we are like ſtinking carrion in God's Noſtrils; if there were no danger of corruption God would not be at coſt, for the ſalt of the Miniſtry of his word, to prevent it, and to ſeaſon us, that we may be a ſweet ſavour unto him. Here may be repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved unſavoury Miniſters, they have the name of ſalt, but they want the property of ſalt; they want their acrimony, they are not ſeaſoned themſelves, and how ſhould they be likely to ſeaſon others? There are four ſorts of this unſavoury ſalt here to be repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Blind Watchmen, Seers that ſee not, Teachers that teach not, Shepherds that feed not their flock, Dogs that do not or cannot bark, Salt-cellars or Salt-boxes without ſalt, or elſe ſalt without its ſaltneſs; ſuch as have the name indeed of ſalt, but want the virtue of it.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:49739:11"/>2. Heretical Teachers are unſavoury Salt and here to be reproved: <hi>Haeretici,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Auſtin, Cimicibus ſimiles, vivi mordent, mortui foetent,</hi> they are like Gnats, that bite whilſt alive, and ſtink when they are dead. <hi>Infatuantur Doctores,</hi> ſaith <hi>Maldonat in loc. Cum malè docent, aut malè aedificant.</hi> Theſe eſpecially are unſavoury ſalt or worſe, who do not onely not ſeaſon, but poyſon their People, <hi>Qui pravo ſapore in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiunt:</hi> 'tis a ſaying of <hi>Maldonat, Degeneres Doctores, haeretici, imprimis,</hi> are good for nothing, <hi>Niſi ut con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culcentur, niſi ut crementur.</hi> Degenerate Doctours, Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks chiefly, are good for nothing, but to be trodden under foot, but to be burnt; but that they are in his ſenſe to be ſalted with fire, becauſe they are unſavoury, ſhall be no determination of mine; If a Proteſtant Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter ſhould fall away to Popery, and become a Maſs-Prieſt, and after return again to the Reformed Church, by true repentance, he may be thereupon readmitted to be a Teacher and Paſtour amongſt us, but ſuch ſurely ought to be humbled for their Apoſtacy, and may do well to have before their Eyes, the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of <hi>Ecebolius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezekiel</hi> 44.10, 11, 12, 13.</note> who having often denyed the Faith, and after return'd to the truth, threw himſelf down at the Church Door, and cried out. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, kick me or tread upon me inſenſible Salt. 3. A third ſort of unſavoury ſalt may be reckoned a Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher that preaches onely general truths, but without application to his Hearers: the uſe is the Salt and the Soul too of a Sermon; <hi>Generalia non pungunt.</hi> Such Preachers are like Fencers, that make a great flouriſh, but never ſtrike to purpoſe; like thoſe Trumpets that give an uncertain ſound, and who then ſhall prepare himſelf to the Battel? 4. Here are to be reproved thoſe that have Salt for others, but have no Salt in
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:49739:12"/> themſelves; or are unſeaſoned themſelves, ſuch as preach well, but live ill; whoſe unſavoury Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, makes that the word doth not ſeaſon others, as it ſhould, but becometh unfruitfull. Oh what will become of you unſavoury Salt! Expect you may, to be caſt out, and to be trodden under foot of Men. Oh abſurd and unreaſonable Men, you have a holy Calling and lead an unholy Life: You call your ſelves ſpiritual Perſons, and the Spiritualty, and yet live af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the fleſh; the Miniſters of God, and yet are really the Servants of Sin. If there be not ſuch a thing as Religion, why do you preach it? if there be, why do you not live it? take heed, leſt while you preach to ſome others, your ſelves become not caſt-aways; leſt while you offer Heaven to others, you fall ſhort of it your ſelves; leſt whilſt you warn others to take heed of Hell, you your ſelves fall into it. And ſo I come to the third ſort of uſes, and they are of exhortation, and that both to the Miniſters, and to the People. And firſt to the Miniſters, Are the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters ſalt? then labour to be like ſalt.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Labour for the Whiteneſs and Purity of Salt, get pure Hearts, be of a pure Lip: and ſith ye are compared to Salt conſider what manner of Perſons ye ought to be, in all holy Converſation and Godlineſs.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Labour for the acrimony of ſalt, be unto ſinners a Reprover. Salt is more neceſſary than Sugar; ſharp words, than ſweet and pleaſing words, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent the corruption of manners amongſt your Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</p>
            <p n="3">3. When ſinners are wounded for their ſins, do ye ſtanch their bleeding wounds and keep them from rankling, do ye preach the Goſpel to wounded Conſciences.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:49739:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>4. Be ye univerſal Antidotes and Preſervatives a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Corruption every way, againſt corrupt Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and corrupt Affections, againſt corrupt Spee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches and againſt all thoſe Children that are corrupt. Yea labour to have ſalt in your ſelves, that ye may be able to ſeaſon others. Labour for the Salt of Grace, that you may preach, out of your own hearts, from the Heart to the Heart, oh that you may not want that Grace, which you exhort others to get and grow in. You that perſwade others to be gracious, be ſure you be ſuch your ſelves. Labour to feel the power of that Religion you preach to others, and then preach the power that you feel. Be able to ſay with the Apoſtles, that which we have ſeen and heard de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare we unto you, that ye alſo may have Fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip with us. But if the Queſtion be here, whether a Man cannot be a true Miniſter, and his preaching profitable to others, except he have ſaving Grace himſelf? Our Anſwer muſt be, that ſaving Grace, is not abſolutely neceſſary, to the being of a Miniſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: A Man may be a Miniſter, although he have not the real and ſaving work of Grace in his Heart. <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das</hi> was an Apoſtle called and ſent out by Chriſt, and (for ought we know) ſuccesfull too in his Miniſtry: and yet he was a Caſt-away. The Miniſtry, ſaith one, is <hi>Gratia gratis data,</hi> not <hi>Gratia gratum faciens.</hi> 'Tis appointed for the good of the Church, of the Body of Chriſt, and not moſtly or chiefly for his own good, that is the Preacher of it. And you that are private Chriſtians ought to know, that the effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of the word and Sacraments, doth not depend upon the holineſs or worthineſs of the Miniſter, but upon the Ordinance, and Inſtitution and Bleſſing of Chriſt; the ſeed may grow that is ſowed by a foul hand: The Phyſick may work well and do good,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:49739:13"/> though perhaps the Phyſician lives contrary to his own Preſcription and Rules of Phyſick. And what though your Miniſter ſhould have <hi>Jacob</hi>'s Voice and <hi>Eſau</hi>'s Hands? or ſhould be like a ſile, that ſmooths other things, and remains rough it ſelf? the Law is not to be condemned, becauſe ſome Profeſſours of it are the Breakers of it, and are lawleſs themſelves. The letter it not the worſe, becauſe brought to you by the hands of a diſhoneſt and wicked Carrier. Our Saviour hath determined this caſe, <hi>Math.</hi> 23.23. The Scribes and Phariſees, (ſaith he) ſit in <hi>Moſes</hi>'s Seat; all therefore, whatſoever they thus bid you ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, obſerve and do; but do not ye after their works, for they ſay and do not: as long as they preached the Doctrine of <hi>Moſes,</hi> they were to be heard and ſo far obeyed. 'Tis true, it cannot be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied but that 'tis a Miniſter's Duty, to be good and gracious, righteous and really holy himſelf, aſwell as to preach, and make others holy, and to turn o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers unto righteouſneſs: If Miniſters be notoriouſly ſcandalous in their Converſation, it belongs to the Governours of the Church, to caſt out ſuch as are unſavoury Salt. Yet whilſt ſuch as theſe, who preach well and live ill, are in the Church, the People may hear them, and profit too, by their Miniſtry. We muſt not tye God to the goodneſs of any Man's Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: He is of infinite Power and Wiſedom; he can write well with a bad Pen; and cut well with a blunt and bad Knife; and ſtrike a ſtrait ſtroke with a crooked Rule or Line; he that awakened <hi>Peter</hi>'s Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience to repentance with the crowing of a Cock, can by the Trumpet of the Goſpel, though blown or ſounded by a bad Miniſter, awake them that ſleep, yea that are dead in their ſins and treſpaſſes, make them ſtand up from the dead, and Chriſt ſhall give
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:49739:13"/> them Life. Labour for the Salt of Learning, for a competent knowledge, at leaſt, in the Tongues, Arts and Sciences, in the <hi>Hebrew, Greek</hi> and <hi>Latin</hi> Tongues; the Languages are the Cabinets, wherein the Jewels of all Truths both divine and humane are laid up. Skill in the Languages, is a Key that opens, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locks all theſe Cabinets, and lets a Man into the knowledge of them all; And then as for Arts and Sciences, labour for ſome meaſure of theſe, of Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gick, moral and natural Philoſophy, Rhetorick, Hiſtory, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> What good is and may be had of theſe, a Reverend Authour of our own Mr. <hi>Reyner,</hi> hath excellently ſhewn, in a Treatiſe to this purpoſe, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled, a Treatiſe of the neceſſity of humane Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, for a Goſpel Preacher. Theſe, theſe are good Handmaids to Divinity, though not lookt on as the Queen. 3. Labour for the Salt of Wiſedom, that you may know how to ſpeak a word in ſeaſon to him that is weary; that you may be able to ſpeak as a Goſpel-Preacher ought to ſpeak; as a Workman that needeth not to be aſhamed, rightly dividing the word of truth as a good Steward, giving to every one of the Family his proper portion; as a wiſe Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-builder laying the Foundation aright, and buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding upon the Rock Chriſt; then rearing up an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable Superſtructure, <hi>viz.</hi> Gold, Silver, precious Stones, not wood, hay and ſtubble, leſt when the fiery Trial come, your works be burnt up, though you ſhould be ſaved, but ſo as by Fire, but ſo as to be like a Brand pluckt out of the Fire. Be wiſe as Serpents, be wiſer than the old Serpent, that ye may know and prevent or diſappoint, his Wiles, Stra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegems, Methods and cunning Craftineſs, whereby he lies in wait to deceive and beguile unwary Souls.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:49739:14"/>2. Labour to ſeaſon others alſo by your teaching, and by your Living. Labour to imitate our great Lord, Maſter, Doctour and Biſhop of our Souls, the Apoſtle and High-Prieſt of our Profeſſion, Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, of whom <hi>Cyprian,</hi> the Father, tells us, <hi>Dominus in verbis, Doctor &amp; conſummator in factis, docens quid fieret, &amp; faciens quodcunque docuiſſet.</hi> Preach and Practiſe, ſay and do both, that thoſe that hear your good Sermons, and ſee your good Works, may be perſwaded to go and do likewiſe; and ſo you and they may be bleſſed in the deed. Be not like the Carpenters which builded <hi>Noah</hi>'s Ark, who were not wrought upon by <hi>Noah</hi>'s Preaching, nor by their own working about the Ark, and ſo at laſt were themſelves drowned in the Flood. Never dream, that your Names and Titles, or that your Places and Callings will ſave you, if you prove unſavoury ſalt, heretical, idle, profane, unfaithfull Miniſters. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider how ſeverely God puniſhed <hi>Nadab</hi> and <hi>Abihu,</hi> the Sons of <hi>Aaron,</hi> though thought to be good Men, for doing the Work of the Lord negligently, ſo offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring ſtrange Fire before the Lord, <hi>Lev.</hi> 10.1, 2. How remarkably he puniſhed <hi>Hophni</hi> and <hi>Phinehaz</hi> the bad Sons of a good Father, and the Poſterity of <hi>Eli</hi> afterwards for the wickedneſs of thoſe Prieſts, and becauſe <hi>Eli</hi> their Father the High-Prieſt reſtrained them not! See, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.30. Wherefore I ſaid in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, thy Houſe and the Houſe of thy Father ſhould walk before me for ever, but now, the Lord ſaith; be it far from me, for them that honour me, I will honour, and they that deſpiſe me ſhall be lightly eſteemed. <hi>Eli</hi> the Judge the High-Prieſt was deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from <hi>Ithamar,</hi> the ſecond Son of <hi>Aaron</hi> the High-Prieſt; ſee, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 24.3. and therefore ſome think that the High-Prieſts of <hi>Eleazar</hi>'s Family, had ſome
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:49739:14"/> way provoked God by their wickedneſs, in former Judges times, and that therefore God had removed the High-Prieſt-hood unto the Houſe of <hi>Ithamar,</hi> of whom <hi>Eli</hi> was; and now again becauſe of the ſins of <hi>Eli</hi>'s Sons, <hi>Hophni</hi> and <hi>Phinehaz,</hi> God threatens to remove the High-Prieſt-hood from <hi>Eli</hi> his houſe and family. And ſo we find that King <hi>Solomon</hi> depoſed <hi>Abiathar</hi> from being High-Prieſt, who was of the Sons of <hi>Eli,</hi> and put <hi>Zadok</hi> in his room; <hi>That the word of the Lord might be fulfilled, which he ſpake con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Houſe of</hi> Eli <hi>in</hi> Shiloh, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 2.27. <hi>Hophni</hi> and <hi>Phinehaz</hi> were ſlain with the ſword of the <hi>Philiſtins</hi> in their Father's days; <hi>Eli</hi> himſelf came alſo to a violent death: and afterwards in King <hi>Saul</hi>'s reign were ſlain fourſcore and five Prieſts at one time, 'tis thought of the houſe and lineage of <hi>Eli.</hi> Oh con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider this ye Prieſts that forget God, and by unſavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rineſs make the people to abhor the ſacrifices of the Lord, leſt he tear you in pieces, and there be none to deliver you. Ye Prieſts that are unſavoury may expect to be made a ſacrifice, and to be ſalted with Fire. Woe unto you Scribes and Phariſees and Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites, how ſhall ye eſcape the damnation of Hell? Remember and conſider how King <hi>Joſiah</hi> burnt the Idolatrous Prieſts bones on the Altar, and how the King of <hi>Babylon</hi> roſted the adulterous Prieſts with fire.</p>
            <p>And now, oh that Heads and Fellows of Colleges in the Univerſities would conſider, that their Colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges are as ſo many Store-houſes of Salt, and that to them belong the ſeaſoning of Youth; the fitting of them for Church and State; the whole Land comes to you for ſalt, as the <hi>Egyptians</hi> did to <hi>Joſeph</hi>'s Grana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries for Corn. If the ſalt of Knowledge, of Grace, of Wiſedom fail here, it may cauſe a famine worſe
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:49739:15"/> than a famine of Bread, even a famine of the word of the Lord. If ye become unſavoury, I cannot promiſe you, but that as the Societies of the Knights Templers of old, and the Religious Houſes of Monks and Nuns, in King <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth's days, were diſſolved, ye may be one day caſt out alſo. Oh that the people of <hi>England</hi> may never have cauſe to come to the King and Parliament to complain, as the men of <hi>Jericho</hi> did to <hi>Eliſha,</hi> 2 <hi>King.</hi> 2.19. ſaying, <hi>Behold, we pray thee the ſituation of this City is plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant, but the water is naught, and the ground barren.</hi> Theſe Colleges and Schools of Learning are well built, well ſituated, well endowed, fine pleaſant ſeats, but the fountains of water which ariſe here, and ſhould make glad the City of God are naught, and the ground about barren and unfruitfull, brings forth little to the glory of God, or the benefit of the Church, or the Commonwealth. If ever ſuch com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint ſhould be, and that juſtly, the leaſt you can look for, Maſters, Fathers and Brethren, is, that our Sovereign, adviſed by his great Council, ſhould ſay, as <hi>Elijah, Bring me hither a new Cruſe, and put ſalt therein;</hi> call for new Heads and new Fellows, and ſuch as have ſalt in them, of Learning, Grace, Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and put them into theſe ſprings, that ſo the waters may be healed, and there may be here and from henceforth no more dearth, or barren Land.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, here is an uſe of exhortation to the people. Are Miniſters ſalt? then let them look on ſuch as very uſefull and neceſſary; they are as neceſſary as Stars in the Firmament, as Shepherds to a Flock, as Labourers in Harveſt, as Salt at a Table. They are neceſſary to them that are called and uncalled. For the firſt, the Scripture tells us <hi>Faith comes by hearing, and by hearing of the word of God;</hi> but how ſhall they
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:49739:15"/> hear without a Preacher? and how ſhall they preach except they be ſent? As for thoſe that are called and juſtified, they alſo have need of, have uſe of the ſalt of the Miniſtry, of the ſalt of the Word, <hi>Nè denuò occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pati putrefactione, recidant in corruptionem &amp; putre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factionem:</hi> ſo <hi>Chemnitius:</hi> leſt they fall away again to the curruption that is in the world through luſt. 2. Be exhorted to prize them highly, and to purchaſe them what-e'er they coſt, buy them and ſell them not. Pray God to make good his promiſe, that though he ſhould feed you with the bread of adverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and the water of affliction, yet he would not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move your Teachers any more into corners, but that your eyes may ſee your Teachers, God would not allow that the Prieſts of <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſhould ſell their Cities, and <hi>Joſeph</hi> would not buy for <hi>Pharaoh</hi> the Land of the Prieſts in <hi>Egypt,</hi> when he bought all the Land beſides; do not puniſh and ſtarve your Miniſters; if you would have ſalt, let them not want bread. 3. Uſe them, ſit at their feet, and receive words from their lips, even the words of eternal life. Say, and that heartily, whatever you ſpeak unto us from the Lord that we will do: yea prize and uſe the holy Scriptures; let your ſpeeches and diſcourſes be ſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with this ſalt; and whilſt you feed your Bodies, feed your Souls with the word of God, or diſcourſe about it. <hi>Polydore Virgil, De communi vita Sacerdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum,</hi> obſerves, that the Fathers brought in the read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Scriptures at Meals, <hi>Nè</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ſolae vobis fauces ſumant cibum, ſed &amp; aures eſuriant verbum Dei,</hi> that their Ears might hunger after the word of God, as well as their Palates to taſte their bodily food. 4. Do what you can in your places, according to your abilities, to help others that want, to ſome of this ſalt, I mean to good Miniſters, and to the preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:49739:16"/> of the word. How holy and happy might we be if there were of this ſavoury ſalt in every Pariſh in <hi>England!</hi> and that every Miniſter might have a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable and honourable maintenance, and none have cauſe to complain of his poor Salary! if in every Candleſtick there were burning and ſhining Lights! and that there were ſufficient maintenance, or Oil for every Lamp amongſt us! Are Miniſters ſalt? then bear with them when they uſe acrimony in their preaching, when they reprove us ſharply, and make our wounds ſmart. As long as we are fleſh and bloud and liable to corruption, the ſalt of reproof and admonition will be neceſſary, uſefull and beneficial to us. Without the ſalt of the word, the Devil (that <hi>Beelzebub</hi>) will fly-blow us, and breed in us ſuch worms of Conſcience that without Repentance will never dye. Say and pray let a faithfull Miniſter ſalt me, or ſmite me with his reproof, it ſhall be a kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, it ſhall be as an excellent Oil, that ſhall not break my Head.</p>
            <p>To conclude all, ſith theſe words are underſtood by ſome, of Chriſtians in general, and of others of Miniſters, let us all, both Miniſters and People, pray and endeavour to be the ſalt of the earth, to have ſalt in our ſelves, and to ſeaſon others, theſe words (ſaith <hi>Chemnitius) Rectè accìpiuntur partim ut doctrina ſeu commonefactio, partim ut promiſſio:</hi> partly as an admonition or doctrine, and partly as a promiſe: ſo, let us then put this promiſe in ſuit in the Court of Heaven by our earneſt and fervent Prayers, that God would make us the ſalt of the earth, and ſavoury ſalt, that we may be good for ſomething, and never be caſt out of his Church here, and kept out of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and caſt into outer darkneſs hereafter.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
